{"tossups": [{"question": "Howard Beale suggested that this period was born out of politicians\u2019 exploitative desires. The sitting president during this period was labeled a racist by Kenneth Stampp, who portrayed his opponents as noble crusaders. William Archibald Dunning led a school of thought about this period which condemned this period as \u201cthe nadir of national disgrace.\u201d This period was termed \u201cAmerica\u2019s Unfinished Revolution\u201dby Eric Foner, who argues against the historical treatment of this period that blamed scalawags and carpetbaggers for its failings. For the point, name this period of American history, during which the South was brought back within the Union after the Civil War.", "answer": "<b> Reconstruction</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Victor Ostrovsky claimed that the charges against this man were doctored by the Israelis in retaliation for this man\u2019s criticism of the invasion of Lebanon. This man helped organize Paul McCartney concerts in Cambodia to help the region recover from Pol Pot. This man claimed that he was not aware of the Jasenovac concentration camp while serving in the Balkans during Operation Kozara. Despite the revelation that this man served as an interpreter for Army Group E in the Wehrmacht, this man became President of Austria in 1986. For the point, name this fourth Secretary-General of the UN.", "answer": "Kurt<b> Waldheim</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Vladimir Lenin\u2019s older brother was hanged for plotting the death of one ruler of this name on the sixth anniversary of the assassination of another ruler of this name by the Narodnaya Volya. In an accident near Borki Station, one ruler with this name held up a collapsed train roof to help his children escape. Alaska was sold to the U.S. by the second tsar of this name, and the Decembrist revolt broke out after the death of the first tsar of this name. For the point, give this name shared by three Romanov tsars, including the emancipator of the serfs.", "answer": "<b> Alexander</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "After this battle, the message \u201cwe will never leave Mike Durant\u201d was repeatedly broadcast. The goal of this battle was to capture the warlord Mohammed Farah Aidid. Randy Shughart received a posthumous Medal of Honor for defending the pilot of<em> Super Six-Four</em>, one of two helicopters that crashed during this battle. For the point, name this 1993 battle, the subject of<em> Black Hawk Down</em>, in which 18 American soldiers were killed in the capital of Somalia.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Mogadishu</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "In a film depiction of this battle, a general says \u201cDon\u2019t hurry. Let the [...] wedge close in. Let Buslai engage them\u201d as a white-robed army approaches. Sergei Eisenstein depicted this battle in a 1938 film that fostered a legend that many Livonian soldiers fell and drowned here. For the point, name this 1242 battle, a victory for Prince of Novgorod Alexander Nevsky over a branch of the Teutonic Knights that took place on the frozen Lake Peipus.", "answer": "Battle of (or on) the<b> Ice</b> (accept Battle of<b> Lake Peipus</b> before said)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "One head of this organization drafted the Worldwide Attack Matrix, and its predecessor was led by\u201cWild Bill\u201d Donovan. This organization\u2019s Sidney Gottlieb gave people LSD in Project MKULTRA. The downfalls of Jacobo Arbenz and Mohammed Mossadegh were orchestrated by this organization, which operated an aircraft whose pilot refused to use a suicide pill after crashing near Yekaterinburg. Gary Powers flew a U-2 plane for, for the point, what U.S. government agency that succeeded the OSS in its mission of spying on foreign powers?", "answer": "<b> C</b>entral<b> I</b>ntelligence<b> A</b>gency", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This man had an African slave scrub his own skin to prove that he was not covered in ink; that event was recounted in the letters of Luis Frois. This man\u2019s conflict with Saito Dosan ended with his marriage to Saito\u2019s daughter Lady Nohime [no-HEE-may]. This man was forced to commit seppuku after being betrayed by Akechi Mitsuhide at Honno-ji. For the point, name this first of Japan\u2019s Three Great Unifiers, a leader who employed Toyotomi Hideyoshi and Tokugawa Ieyasu.", "answer": "<b> Oda</b> Nobunaga", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man forced his enemies to withdraw to Castle William after falsely boasting about the size of his army. That incident occurred when this man\u2019s ship<em> Liberty</em> was seized following a dispute over a wine shipment. This first governor of an independent Massachusetts was closely aligned with Samuel Adams, and neither of them were pardoned by Thomas Gage following the Boston Tea Party. For the point, name this chair of the Continental Congress who legendarily wanted to aid King George III\u2019s troubled vision by signing the Declaration of Independence in exceptionally large print.", "answer": "John<b> Hancock</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man was made surveyor-general of victualling during the Second Anglo-Dutch War. He used a form of shorthand known as tachygraphy [tacky-graphy], and employed several foreign languages when describing affairs with women such as Deborah Willet. He wrote about using tobacco to ward off the Great Plague and described ascending the Tower of London to witness the \u201clamentable\u201d Great Fire of London. For the point, name this Londoner who chronicled everyday life from 1660 to 1669 in his extensive diary.", "answer": "Samuel<b> Pepys</b> ([PEEPS], but be lenient)", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "This treaty provided for the religious freedom of the Sephardi Jews. Despite the success of Jacques Massu in maintaining civilian order, the harsh tactics he used helped push forward this treaty. One signatory to this treaty was granted usage of the naval base and underground nuclear testing facility at Mers el Kebir. Though it was opposed by the right-wing OAS, this treaty was signed by the FLN and the government of Charles de Gaulle. For the point, name this 1962 treaty that ended the Algerian War of Independence.", "answer": "<b>\u00b4Evian</b> Accords", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "For the point, name this crime committed by Aldrich Ames and Robert Hanssen, who divulged the identities of numerous CIA double agents to the KGB.", "answer": "<b> spying for Russia</b> and/or the<b> Soviet Union</b> or<b> USSR</b> (accept equivalent descriptions, like being a<b> double agent for the Russians</b>; prompt on descriptions of espionage that don\u2019t mention \u201cfor Russia;\u201d prompt on treason before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "TEU Article 50 deals with the legality of this cause. Nigel Farage is a staunch proponent of this cause. Citing a desire to prevent the erosion of democracy, Boris Johnson came out in favour of this cause in February 2016. It will be settled on June 23rd following a promise by David Cameron to hold a referendum. For the point, name this cause championed by UKIP, the UK Independent Party, that involves leaving a European community based in Brussels.", "answer": "United Kingdom (or Great Britain or England)<b> exit</b>ing the<b> E</b>uropean<b> U</b>nion (accept<b> Brexit</b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "A document found near the site of this event is addressed \u201cTo Boddah\u201d and ends by quoting Neil Young\u2019s lyric \u201cit\u2019s better to burn out than to fade away.\u201d This event was the subject of private detective Tom Grant\u2019s film<em> Soaked in Bleach</em>. It nearly happened a month earlier in Rome, which was noted at the end of the documentary<em> Montage of Heck</em>. After this event, Sweet 75 was formed by Krist Novoselic, while Dave Grohl formed Foo Fighters. Courtney Love questioned whether this event was a murder. For the point, name this 1994 event in which the frontman of Nirvana ended his life.", "answer": "<b> death</b> of Kurt<b> Cobain</b> (accept suicide or equivalents; accept shooting or equivalents)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "Near the end of this event, a leader wrote that \u201cYou can be sure that we will resist with determination, whatever the case,\u201d noting that an attack was \u201calmost imminent.\u201d The \u201cArmageddon Letter\u201d was written by Fidel Castro during this event, shortly before a concession to remove Jupiter installations from Turkey placated Nikita Khrushchev. In its aftermath, the Moscow-to-Washington hotline was created. For the point, name this event in which, over 13 days in October 1962, the Soviets and Americans nearly instigated a nuclear war over the deployment of Soviet nukes in the Caribbean.", "answer": "<b> Cuban Missile</b> Crisis (accept<b> October</b> Crisis or<b> Caribbean</b> Crisis early; accept equivalents for crisis)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Albrecht von Wallenstein\u2019s greatest victory took place in one of these locations named Dessau. A famous painting of the battle of Arcole shows Napoleon with a French standard at one of these locations, and the battle of Luding was fought at one of these locations during the Long March. The Earl of Surrey retreated to Berwick after being defeated by William Wallace at one of these locations named Stirling, and Harold Hadrada was killed at a battle named for one of these locations at Stamford. For the point, name these structures that include the Golden Gate.", "answer": "<b> Bridges</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s trek from Indiana to Florida was recounted in his \u201cA Thousand Miles to the Gulf.\u201d The Lone Pines earthquake helped lend credibility to this man\u2019s theory on the formation of the Owens Valley. He broke with Gifford Pinchot following a disagreement over logging and grazing in forest reserves. This opponent of the damming of the Hetch Hetchy reservoir was notably photographed overlooking Glacier Point alongside Theodore Roosevelt in Yosemite National Park. For the point, name this naturalist and founder of the Sierra Club.", "answer": "John<b> Muir</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "This conflict was preceded by the Orlov rebellion and encouraged by the \u201cFriendly Society.\u201d George Canning helped organize one intervention in this conflict through the Treaty of London, and it was ended by the Treaty of Constantinople. The Pruth River was crossed by Alexander Ypsilantis in this conflict, which included a massacre at Chios and the naval battle of Navarino. For the point, name this conflict in which revolutionaries on the Peloponnese fought the Ottoman Empire.", "answer": "<b> Greek War of Independence</b> (or equivalent descriptions)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s most notable deed was recorded within the Catalan Atlas. This man waged war against the Mossi peoples, where he was served by the general Sagmandia. Djingeureber Mosque was built by this man\u2019s architect as-Saheli, as was Sankore University. Maghan succeeded this man whose most notable action saw him travel through Cairo and Medina while legendarily handing out large amounts of golden coins. For the point, name this king of Mali known for his extravagant hajj to Mecca.", "answer": "Mansa<b> Musa</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man, who proclaimed \u201cLiberty and Union, now and forever, one and inseparable!\u201d, signed a treaty with British diplomat Lord Ashburton. For the point, name this Massachusetts Whig senator who, with Clay and Calhoun, dominated the Senate in the 19th century.", "answer": "Daniel<b> Webster</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "One man with this title was converted to Catholicism by Pedro Paenz, who later was succeeded by the insolent Alfonso Mendes. That man with this title was Susenyos I, who was a part of the Gondarian line. Seven years after the Shewan line gained control of this title, its leader defeated the Italians at Adowa. Another person to hold this title is venerated as the messiah in Rastafarianism. Menelik II and other members of the Solomonic Dynasty held, for the point, what ruling position over an African country, last held in 1975 by Haile Selassie?", "answer": "<b> Emperor of Ethiopia</b> (accept<b> negusa nagast</b>; prompt on \u201cKing of Kings\u201d)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "Prior to this battle, a case of dermatitis sidelined a leader of the eventual winning side. Raymond Spruance and Frank Fletcher teamed up in this battle, which occurred at objective AF, as the breaking of JN-25b predicted. On the second day of this battle, the carriers<em> Akagi</em> and<em> Hiryu</em> sank, though it resulted in the decommissioning of the<em> USS Yorktown</em>. For the point, name this battle in which Chester Nimitz halted Isoroku Yamamoto\u2019s advance, turning the momentum of the Pacific Theater.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Midway</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A controversy involving this man arose after retired serviceman Tim Terpak was honored at a New York Rangers game. In an interview in<em> Stars and Stripes</em> magazine, this man claimed not to have heard that three Chinooks were actually an hour ahead of him. In Febraury 2015, he retracted his false claims about having been in a helicopter that was hit by an RPG in Iraq. For the point, name this journalist who was replaced by Lester Holt, a decade after this man replaced Tom Brokaw as anchor of<em> NBC Nightly</em> <em>News</em>.", "answer": "Brian<b> Williams</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "John Alcock and Arthur Brown received a<em> Daily Mail</em> Prize for performing this action. Ren\u00b4e Fonck\u2019s attempt to perform this action ended with the deaths of Charles Clavier and Jacob Sclaroff, in part due to Fonck\u2019s insistence on bringing a refrigerator and sofa. The Orteig Prize was established for any Allied pilot that could perform this action, which was first completed on May 21, 1927. For the point, what action was completed by<em> The Spirit of St. Louis</em>, for the first time without breaks or a co-pilot, by Charles Lindbergh?", "answer": "<b> transatlantic flight</b> (accept descriptions of<b> crossing</b> the<b> Atlantic</b> Ocean by<b> plane</b>; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This disease\u2019s<em> Vollum</em> strain was isolated on Gruinard Island. The largest recorded outbreak of this disease devastated the cattle population during the Rhodesian Bush War. Bruce Edward Ivins was largely suspected of sending samples of this disease to Senators Tom Daschle and Patrick Leahy with the message\u201cDeath to America, death to Israel, Allah is great.\u201d For the point, name this diseased spread by spores that was stored in envelopes during various 2001 terrorist attacks, frequently used as a bioweapon.", "answer": "<b> anthrax</b> (or<b> bacillus anthracis</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The 1895 case<em> Sparf v. US</em> ruled that these groups of people do not have to be told that they have the right of nullification. In<em> Williams v. Florida</em> ruled that the size of these groups of people is flexible, though<em> Ballew v. Georgia</em> determined 5 to be too small. These groups are to be \u201cimpartial\u201d according to the Sixth Amendment, which guarantees access to one of these groups in all criminal trials. For the point, name these groups of people, usually 12, who are tasked with rendering verdicts.", "answer": "<b> jury</b> (do not accept grand jury)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The myth that this person was buried between platforms 9 and 10 in King\u2019s Cross station inspired J.K. Rowling. This leader\u2019s army was encircled by their own families and unable to retreat in a defeat at the hands of Gaius Suetonius Paulinus at the Battle of Watling Street. This ruler led the Iceni and Trinovantes tribes in burning down Camulodunum. Tacitus and Cassius Dio disagree on whether this woman committed suicide after her defeat near present-day London. For the point, name this queen of the Iceni tribe who revolted against Rome during Nero\u2019s reign.", "answer": "<b> Boudica</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "Legendarily, the Roman Stoic Epictetus claimed he would rather die than lose this possession, which defined him as a philosopher. A satirical treatise by the Roman emperor Julian the Apostate opposed these things, which were partly destroyed in a Spartan punishment for cowards. According to Cassius Dio, Hadrian was the first Roman emperor to consistently maintain this aesthetic item. For the point, name this appendage long-prized on older Greek men but long-deprecated in Rome, a type of facial hair.", "answer": "<b> beard</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s philanthropic efforts included founding a School of Music in his home city of Rochester, New York. This man, who suffered from spinal pain late in life, wrote a suicide note reading \u201cTo my friends: my work is done. Why wait?\u201d This man\u2019s company, founded on the strength of David Houston\u2019s patent for a roll film holder, filed for bankruptcy in 2012, having failed to adjust to digital photography. For the point, name this entrepreneur who founded Kodak.", "answer": "George<b> Eastman</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}], "bonuses": []}